This program is brought to you by
Stanford on iTunes at stanford
University. Please visit us at
iTunes.stanford.edu.
They behave
oddly. I've showed you some
uh interference of light waves when they
go through slits and that sort of thing.
uncertainty principles for particles and
a photon is a particle. So it uh shares
the uncertainty principle with other
particles. But perhaps the the really
simplest context, the simplest system
for studying the basic fundamental
difference between classical thinking
and quantum thinking is the polarization
of a photon. If we forget everything
else about the
photon, assume that it's going in a
particular direction, let's say down the
z-axis with a very specific momentum,
then the only thing that's left to
discuss about the photon is the
direction in which it's
polarized. that
polarization degree of freedom forms a
kind of mini quantum system that has um
more insight in it I think or more
insight can be gained from it than I
think thinking about almost any other
simple quantum mechanical system. So I
want to go through we we started it last
time. I want to continue but first I
want to review a little
bit. First of all you can how should you
think about the polarization of the
photon? Well a photon is going into the
blackboard. All right. So we need not
worry about its direction of motion. We
need not worry about its momentum. We
need only worry about this little
vector. This sort of little flag that
the photon carries with
it. It moves into the blackboard. Let's
see. That's a bad color, isn't it? It
moves into the blackboard. That's an
even worse color.
Didn't bring your own this time. I
didn't bring my own this time. I tell
them every time to please leave me pens.
Ah the photon is going into the
blackboard
good and we can think of the plane
perpendicular to the motion of the
photon and in that plane there's a kind
of little flag a little the little flag
can
point in any direction in the xy plane
the photons moving in the z direction.
This is the xy plane x and y and in a
certain sense to be specified and only
to be correctly defined when we think
about it quantum
mechanically the little flag can point
in any direction in the xy plane. So
photons carry little
flags. The flags are their polarization
vector. The polarization vector is
perpendicular to the motion of the
photon.
But it's an odd little flag. It has some
very peculiar properties. So let's uh
let's first of all go through some of
the simple properties that it has
uh and why it is so odd. First of all,
you can send the photon through
polarizers. Now
polarizers are really not terribly
quantum mechanical necessarily
necessarily. As I mentioned, I think the
previous time, if you send microwaves or
radio waves through a
grid, a grid of
wires like
so, the photons or better yet, there are
rad, well, not better yet, but the radio
waves or the microwaves that go through
it will come out on the other side
polarized. And the reason the best way
the easiest way to think about it is to
think about it in the language of waves
electric and magnetic fields. The
electric field can
vibrate vertically and
horizontally but it can only drive
current in the vertical direction. Now a
mirror is a system such that when an
electromagnetic wave falls on it a
conductor an electric conductor is such
that current can flow due to the
electric field in any direction and the
flow of that current produces its own
wave and typically what it does is it
produces the reflected wave that
reflects back off the mirror and that is
why mirrors reflect because they produce
currents in there and those currents
produce the reflected wave. Exactly how
that works, we don't have to worry about
here. But it also works in this grid.
The only difference is that the electric
current can uh the current, sorry, the
electric current can only oscillate in
the vertical
direction. And so as far as the vertical
direction goes, the grid is a mirror. It
reflects waves whose electric field is
vertical.
As far as the horizontal direction goes,
the grid isn't there at all. It uh
cannot the electric wave cannot drive
currents in the horizontal direction. So
it's exactly as if there was no grid
there at all and the photon just goes
straight through. So the result is a
grid like this produces a
electromagnetic wave which is
polarized. The official definition of
the polarization is it's the direction
of the electric field. And so a grid
like this will produce a photon or a
electromagnetic wave polarized this way.
I'll represent that by just drawing my
polarizer as having an axis the axis of
polarization not the axis of the grid
lines but the axis that
uh the electromagnetic wave that goes
through it becomes polarized in. All
right. All right. So, we send in we send
through photons one at a time. And the
photons come through. If they pass
through a polarizer like
this, they come out polarized in the X
direction. Let's call that polarization.
Let's just call it X. And never mind
that we're doing quantum mechanics for
the moment. The photons just come
through. If we send it through a second
polarizer to check to make a
check that it really was polarized
horizontally. If the second polarizer is
also polarized
horizontally then the photon will again
go
through. So we can think of the
polarizer as both a preparer of systems.
It prepares a photon with a particular
polarization and it can also be thought
of of as a detector or better yet a
measuring apparatus that measures the
photon polarization. In particular, if
the photon was horizontally polarized,
it will pass through the horizontal
polarizer. On the other hand, if the
photon was created vertically polarized,
I don't need to put arrows on these
things. It's good enough just to put a
direction. If the photon is created
vertically
[Music]
polarized and the apparatus is
horizontally polarized then the photon
will not go through the apparatus. It
may get reflected or it may just get um
absorbed one or the other. Uh but
whichever it does by monitoring whether
the photon goes through over here or not
you have measured whether the
polarization is vertical or horizontal.
All right. Now, there's nothing terribly
non-class about this. You can easily
imagine a uh classical setup where some
kind of device which let through a
vertical flag would block a horizontal
flag and would admit a vertical flag and
vice versa. There's nothing particularly
and this is entirely
deterministic. If you send the photon,
if the photon is vertically polarized,
it'll pass through. If it's horizontally
polarized, it won't pass through. End of
story.
Nothing out of the ordinary
there. The place where the out of the
ordinary happens is when we add to this
picture the idea of symmetry. Yes.
No, but you could imagine that there are
bullets which have little flags on them.
bullets with little funny shaped
bullets with flags on them like
that and they go through if they're
along the direction of some kind of
slits they get blocked otherwise nothing
special. So classical particles uh could
easily do this kind of thing. The place
where you start to get into trouble
thinking classically is oh one other
thing notice that there are also only
two
possibilities for the photon. It either
goes through or it doesn't go through in
this setup. Now now comes the kicker.
The kicker has to do with symmetry. The
symmetry has is the symmetry of rotation
of the xy plane. If it's possible to
hold your polarizer vertically and it's
possible to hold it horizontally, then
the symmetry of physics which allows you
to rotate things allows
you to construct a polarizer which
points at any
angle. What happens to a photon which
goes through
that? It comes out polarized at an
angle.
Well, you can imagine classical setups.
For example, a kind of setup which would
emit which would allow this particular
kind of bullet to go through. The other
kind of bullet which was polarized
horizontally would not go through. Any
kind of device that I try to think of
like that I tend to find would also
block a bullet that was uh polarized in
some nonvertical or non-h horizontal
direction. For example, if the polarizer
literally consisted of a bunch of um a
grid, a grid like
this, which passed things which were
vertical, block things which are
horizontal, they would also block things
which were not
horizontal. Here's where the kicker is.
The kicker is that these nonvertically
or non-h horizontally polarized photons
may or may not go through this
polarizer. They may or may not go
through with a
probability. What's more, there is only
two
possibilities. The photon doesn't get
broken into pieces. Some piece of it
going through, some piece of it not
going through. There are only two
possibilities and that's it. It either
goes through or it doesn't go through
even though it has been polarized in
some other direction. That's where the
peculiarities of quantum mechanics
start. That's be that's where you begin
to wonder is the photon really behaving
like a particle like a sensible particle
or not? And it gets even weirder and
more mysterious when we start to set up
a theory of the probabilities for the
photons to pass through the respective
polarizers.
That theory is of course quantum
mechanics and it is really quite hard to
think of a classical setup which would
produce the same kind of probability
distributions and how they depend on the
orientation of the polarizers.
I don't think anybody has ever
successfully designed such a thing at
least not in any great generality
uh that would uh do the right thing to
polarize
photons. By design I mean design a
classical apparatus which would do the
right thing. So there are only two
possibilities. The photon either appears
to be polarized up or appears to be
polarized horizontally when you detect
it. when you detect it with a horizontal
polarizer, it either goes through or it
doesn't go through. So, you would be
likely to say there's only two possible
states for the photon. On the other
hand, there's more than two possible
states. There's a continuum of possible
states for the photon. You can polarize
it in any direction. And so, we have a
kind of conflict between discreetness
and
continuity. Continuous direction in
which the photon can be polarized. But
when we monitor it and we detect it,
there are only two possible states, one
or the other. And that's the that's the
mystery of quantum
mechanics. Um it's a conflict between
symmetry on the one hand and
discreetness on the other
hand. Okay. So we were beginning to set
up the theory of polarization.
As I said, it is probably the simplest
context in which to study quantum
mechanics. It doesn't have the full uh
complexity of all of quantum mechanics,
but it's the simplest quantum mechanical
system. All right. So, let's now label
the quantum states of the polarization
of a photon. I will not I will make this
phrase shorter. I will simply say the
quantum states of a photon, but I mean
its polarization. All right? It can be
polarized horizontally. Incidentally,
there is no difference between being
polarized horizontally to the right or
polarized horizontally to the left.
That's why I tend to draw double arrows
on the
polarization. There's no difference
between being polarized to the right or
polarized to the left. If you think
about it for a moment, an
electromagnetic wave will oscillate up
and down. And so there's no sense in
which you can say the polarization is
vertical vers vertically up versus
vertically down. And the photon inherits
that fact.
Polarization you can think of a
polarization vector but it kind of has
two ends. There's no sense in which it
points to the right rather than to the
left. But there is a sense in which it's
pointing horizontal rather than
vertical. So that way it's simpler than
the spin.
Well, uh, they they're they're actually
quite isomorphic to each other. They're
completely parallel, completely
identical mathematics. And the reason
for not doing it this time, the spin, is
because I did it last time, right?
That's the main reason. Uh, some people
find it a little easier to visualize the
polarization of a photon.
uh they're identical systems quantum
mechanically and so we don't really need
to distinguish that. Well, okay, let's
go on. All right, we're going to call
that we're going to give that the name
X. That's the K vector X. It represents
a photon polarized
horizontally. And another way that we
can label it, I'm going to take these
arrows off. I get awfully tired of
drawing arrows and they serve no purpose
whatever since there's no sense of
direction along the
arrow. And I'll also label that one
zero another representation of the
incidentally the vector space of states
is clearly two-dimensional since there
are only two possibilities for the
polarization.
two possibilities for the
polarization X or
Y and we'll label
Y
01. All right. So, several different
representations
uh to to label the states of the photon
polarization.
Yes. more than anything else.
No, it's not totally arbitrary. We want
these vectors to be um to be normalized.
Sums of the squares of the components
should add up to one. That's one of the
rules about state vectors that
corresponds to the total probability for
a state adding up to one. We want them
to be orthogonal to each
other. These two vectors are clearly
orthogonal. Multiply the top by the top
plus the bottom by the bottom.
Incidentally, in order to take the inner
product, you should complex conjugate
one of them. But the complex conjugate
of the bottom one is itself. So it's 1 *
0 + 0 * 1 x y
=
0. They're orthogonal. They're
normalized. They form a
basis. Now it's not completely
um some sense you've chosen your axes so
that those will be in order. Yes, I
have. Now I could
have we will see that these vectors are
somewhat ambiguous. We're going to
calculate the things which really count
and when we calculate what really count
namely probabilities we'll find out that
uh that we can't for example distinguish
this vector and this vector. The fact
that there's something in the first
place and nothing in the second place is
the important thing. And the other
important thing is that the sums of the
squares of them add up to uh sums of the
squares of the uh two components add up
to
one. But this is a convenient basis of
the vectors
uh which represent the two
states. Okay. We also
said that we could define an observable.
An observable means the thing that we
measure or that we record in our little
book. We send a lot of photons through.
If a photon goes through the apparatus,
we say + one. If it doesn't go through
the apparatus, we say minus one. Now
there there's absolutely nothing unique.
I could have said seven and 12. anything
I like just to distinguish the two
possibilities. One and minus one are a
nice uh pair of numbers uh that they're
easy to remember and there's no
particular significance to choosing one
and minus one. Uh it's easy to remember
has a nice symmetry to it. And so what
we'll say is that the x
polarization we'll say has polarization
plus and the y polarization has
polarization minus. Again, what I mean
by that is we send a lot of photons
through an X polarizer. If they pass
through, each time a photon passes
through the X polarizer, we write down a
little plus in our notebook. Each time
it is reflected or whatever else happens
to it, we write down a little minus. And
then we can take statistics. We can
define the observable quantity in the
way that I said and uh label it or
associate it with a quantum mechanical
observable. A quantum mechanical
observable is an operator. I'll put a
little hat on it. If I forget to put a
hat on it, uh as long as it's this big
double P here, it means an operator.
It's an operator whose igen vectors are
X and Y. or one and z or this one and
this
one and it has igen value + one for x
and minus one for
y. That's unique. It uh we
abstractly we know how it acts on any
vector because any vector can be
linearly expanded in x and y. But here's
the statement.
This is equal to x and p on y is equal
to minus y. The igen values are + one
and minus one. And I'm going to label
this thing here just to indicate that
it's a polarizer that it represents
polarization in the xy plane. I'm going
to put a little symbol here that
represents the fact that it has to do
with the xy plane as opposed to some
rotated
direction. Okay. So this is its
definition. This it's an operator. A
linear operator associated with every
linear operator is a matrix. The matrix
associated with
P is the matrix 1 - one. As simple as it
could
be. And it's obvious now that when it
acts on the vector x, let's let it act
on the vector
x. The vector x is represented by 1
0. That matrix times that column vector
1 * 1 is
1. 0 * 1 and 1 * 0 - 1 * 0.
So we see that
the P observable when it acts on the X
vector gives X polarization gives us
back the X polarization vector. But when
it acts sorry when it acts on the Y
polarization
vector it gives
minus the Y polarization vector. So this
is the
unique operator which represents the
observable
[Music]
uh the
observable polarization in the xy
plane. Now in this case we knew what we
wanted. We constructed the vectors and
then we made up an observable and we
concocted it just so it would do what we
wanted it to do. In other cases, and
I'll give you an example of another
case. In other cases, there might be
reasons to focus on an observable on an
operator and ask what its igen vectors
are and what its igen values are. The
example that I've already given you was
for example the momentum. The momentum
was described by an operator minus i d
by dx. I told you what the operator was
and then we found its igen vectors and
its igen values. So sometimes uh it's
more convenient not a question more
convenient. Sometimes we know more about
the vectors and the igen values than we
do about the mathematical structure of
the observable and sometimes we know it
the other way. But
uh either
way
observables have igen values and igen
vectors. The igen vectors are the states
in which the observable has a definite
value and that value is the igen
value. So we're back
uh to the basic foundations of the
subject and the uh and the
postulates as we have an example of
them. Now what if we polarize at 45
degrees? What if we turn our polarizer
through 45 degrees? I know we did this
before, but let's do it again. If we
rotate our polarizer through
45°, then we encounter a new state of
polarization. It's neither X nor
Y. It clearly has it's intuitively
obvious that it has equal probability
when the photon is prepared this way and
then goes through the XY polarizer. it's
intuitively obvious that it will have
equal probability to go through either
the X or the Y polarizer since it's
polarized at 45 degrees. Okay.
So it makes sense then to identify this
polarization which I'll label that
way as 1 over the 2 that's just
there to normalize it
times
x +
y equal
likelihood for the polarization to be up
or horizontal if it goes to the
polarizer which detects x
polarization. We can also represent this
in another way. We can represent it as a
column vector 1 / 2 1 /
two equal coefficients in terms of x in
front of x and in front of
y. All right. What about the other
orthogonal polarization? The other
orthogonal polarization I won't draw it
in here but it points in the orthogonal
direction that's equal to 1 over
two and that can be taken to be now the
one thing we know about it and about the
only thing we really know about it is
that it should be orthogonal to this
vector orthogonal to this vector why
orthogonal to it because it represents a
completely distinct different outcome of
an experiment.
namely the experiment of sending it
through the 45 degree
polarizer. All right. Things which
represent different outcomes, different
definite outcomes of some experiment
should be orthogonal to each other.
Well, a simple vector that's orthogonal
to this would be x - y, not
x -
y or 1 /
2 - 1 over 2. Now, makes no
difference whatever if you put the minus
sign in front of the x with no minus
sign in front of the y or vice versa.
We'll see. It makes no difference. All
we need to do is to choose a second
vector orthogonal to this one. Let's
check that it's
orthogonal. The inner product between
this vector and this vector is the sums
of the x components, the product of the
x components and the product of the y
components. So it's 1 over2 * 1
over2 minus 1 over2 * 1 over2. The
inner product is zero. Again, I didn't
have to worry about complex conjugating
because everything is real. So we can
write
down equals
zero. They're also normalized. The sums
of the squares of the coefficients add
up to one. 1 over2^2 + 1 over
2 is 1. So the two vectors are
another basis. They're a different and
separate basis of states, but they're
just as good as the original basis. The
original basis was the basis 1 0 and 0
1. Here's a second basis. These are also
mutually orthogonal and also
normalized. Roughly speaking, uh well,
you you can see what uh you can see the
point. I don't need to belabor it.
What
happens if we start with a polarizer
polarized at 45 degrees like that? We
send the photon through it. It comes out
the other side and then we send it
through a polarizer which is either
vertical or horizontal. Let's take the
horizontal case.
Then the rule of quantum mechanics is
well let's see what let's begin what is
the state of the photon when it comes
out of the first polarizer. When it
comes out of the first polarizer here it
is it's this. So when it comes out of
the first polarizer the state of the
photon is like that.
What is the probability that if we
measure the observable associated with
the XY polarization that we get plus the
answer is again this goes back to the
basic um the basic postulates. We take
the inner
product of the state that we've
constructed. We take the inner product
of that with the igen vector of the
observable of interest. The observable
of interest is
now this observable and its igen vectors
are x and
y.
So we take the inner product for example
of this with x and we square it. That
will give us the probability that after
having gone through the first polarizer
it also goes through the second
polarizer.
That's the probability that after going
through the first polarizer, it then
goes through the second polarizer. We
could also draw this X as just a
horizontal line
here. What is this? This is the inner
product. Let's write them
down. The bra vector here can be
represented as a row vector 1 0.
The k vector is a column
vector 1 over 2 1 over 2 and
the inner product between them is just 1
over
2 1 * 1 over
2 the probability is the square of
that so I should I shouldn't have
written equals here I should have taken
this
away this is true now and the
probability is the square of this
equal
1/2. Okay, so that's was intuitively
clear in the first place that the
probability for the photon to go through
the second polarizer would be 1/2 since
it was polarized at
45°. Uh likewise, if we ask what's the
probability that it would pass through a
vertical polarizer?
Same
answer, slightly different reason to
calculate that. We would put y
here, but that's also equal one
over
two. And so both both cases we would get
the probability being
1/2. Again, not surprising.
Can we construct an
observable which represents the photon
polarization not in the x not in the
vertical and horizontal
direction but in the 45 degree
directions. Let's see if we can do
that. Let's invent the polarization now
and let's call it this. Let's call it
that way. It has the property that when
it acts on
I wish I had names for these two
vectors. Anybody think of names for the
two
vectors? The slanty vectors.
H I want a name for both of them. I mean
for each of them.
Slash and backslash. Good. Okay. So the
observable associated with slash and
backslash I will define to be plus one
on
slash and I'll define it to
be minus
one on
backslash. What's the observable? Can we
find it? Yeah, it's not hard. Uh I'll
just tell you what the answer is and
then we'll check it.
The matrix that's associated with it is
rather simple. It's 1 1 0
0. Let's check that that acts on slash
to give back slash and acts on backslash
to give back slash. All right. Slash is
just 1 over 2 * 1
1. Where is
it? The one over square root of two here
doesn't here it is.
is slash it's 1 over two * 1
1 if a thing is an igen vector so is any
multiple of it. So we don't need to keep
the square root of two in checking
whether it's an igen vector we do need
to keep the square root of two if we
want to normalize it but if all we want
to do is check for igen
vectorness we need not keep that square
root of two in the problem. All right.
So what does this give? It give 0 * 1 +
1 *
1 1 * 1 + 0 * 1 is
1. So that is in
fact what the observable is supposed to
do on slash. It gives backslash. Let's
now try it on
backslash. 0 1 1 0 on one minus
one. What does that give? 0 * 1 + 1 *
-1 that gives min
-1 1 * 1 is
1. Notice that the right hand side is
the
negative of
backslash. So in fact the observable on
backslash does give minus backslash.
This is equal to
minus 1 minus one.
Okay, so we've actually succeeded in
constructing the observable associated
with 45 degree
polarization. A question would it be
accurate to say then that if you define
the states then you restrict what's
observable?
Um yeah if you if if you if you have a
particular state you may ask you can't
ask what's observable anything is
observable if it's unobservable but you
can ask what is definite given a
particular state let's say slash are
there any quantities which when you
measure them will give you definite
deterministic
answers well if you measure measure the
original
observable, you won't get definite
answers. You'll get a half a probability
one way, a half a probability the other
way. If you start with slash on the
other hand, if you measure this
observable, the polarization at the 45
degree angle, then you will get definite
answers for slash and backslash. This
corresponds of course to sending slash
and backslash through the slashed or
backslashed
polarizers. So it's not right to say
that uh that if you're given a state it
determines what's observable. No, it
determines what's definite. It
determines what's
predictable about measurements on that
state. Another example is if you're
given a wave function, any wave
function, you can measure the position
of the electron and the momentum of the
electron. If you just take a random wave
function, any old wave function, you'll
have a statistical probability for
different momenta and different
positions. Neither will be definite. But
if you take a delta function, which is a
very particular state, delta function of
position, then you measure the position,
it'll be definite. It'll be right where
that delta function says it should be.
If you take a plane wave, a cosine, not
a cosine or sine, but an e to the i kx,
and you measure the momentum, then the
momentum will be definite. So given a
state, it restricts the class of things
which are deterministic. It's not the
right word. Uh what's the right word?
Definite, I suppose.
Certain. Okay. So this is the object the
mathematical representation of the
object which is definite for slash and
backslash
states. It happens that I defined it so
that it's positive. So the igen value is
positive one for slash and negative one
for backslash. I could have defined it
the other way. Then I would have put a
minus sign in front of it but that's not
important. Okay.
Well, so far we have polarizers which
are oriented
uh that way and polarizers which are
oriented that way. We can of course
orient the polarizers in any direction
in any direction in the xy plane. So
let's discuss that possibility.
Now arbitrary angle let's have let's
have a polarizer now which is polarized
in the arbitrary angle theta theta
relative to the horizontal.
Then there's another
polarizer which is orthogonal to this
which is polarized in the perpendicular
direction. Polarized this
way. We don't
need to invent a new label for this.
This is just the polarizer whose angle
is theta plus pi / 2. Pi / 2 is 90°. If
you take theta and you add 90° to it, it
becomes perpendicular. So we can label
the two states theta and theta + pi / 2.
They represent the two orthogonal
combinations. Uh the
two mutually exclusive combinations. is
if you send a photon through any photon
which goes to a theta polarizer will
pass through a second theta polarizer
but it will get blocked by a theta plus
pi /2 polarizer that's a
mouthful the two vectors the two vectors
that go with it if you pass it through
the theta polarizer you get out the
state theta I'm going to tell you what
it is how it's related to uh to the
other
states in a more or less obvious way and
this one will be called theta + p /
2. These two should be orthogonal to
each other, but they're not likely to be
orthogonal to the previous states. In
fact, if this goes to a vertical
polarizer, it won't get blocked or may
get blocked, but it may not get blocked.
So we don't expect this to be orthogonal
to the vertical polarization or the
horizontal polarization or for that
matter the 45 degree polarization. It's
not going but they should be
perpendicular to each other. They should
be orthogonal to each other. Okay. So
let me tell you what this
is. Now the justification for this is
ultimately experimental but it makes
sense. It makes intuitive sense. We're
rotating the horizontal polarization by
an angle theta. We started with that
polarization and the horizontal and now
we rotate it by angle theta. It
shouldn't be too surprising that the
answer is cossine
theta time the x
polarization plus sin
theta time the y
polarization or
equivalently cossine theta sin theta
In fact, cosine theta and sin theta are
simply the components of a vector, a
unit vector along the theta
direction. So that's not too
surprising. How about this
one? This one had better be exactly the
same except wherever you see theta here,
you should stick in theta + p / 2.
So this should be
cosine of theta + p / 2. But what's
the cosine of theta + p /
2? Well, not quite
close. Minus the signus the s of
theta. Cosine of theta + p / 2 is
minus the s of
theta. Let's let's just check why that's
so. All right.
[Music]
Uh here's the sign of theta. Here's the
cosine of theta. Now, here's the plus
p / 2. Okay. Notice that the cosine
of theta + p / 2, that's the x
projection here. The cosine is the x
projection. The cosine here is negative,
but the sign is positive.
So the cosine of theta + p / 2 is
minus the s of
theta s minus sin
theta
x plus the s of theta + /
2* y. But what's the s of theta + p
/
2? That's cosine theta.
Okay. Now we can represent this bottom
case here
by minus
sign
cosine. Okay. This one represents a
photon polarized along theta and this
one represents a photon polarized in the
orthogonal direction. Are these
orthogonal basis vectors? Well, first of
all, are they normalized to unity? In
other words, is the length of them equal
to unity? Well, that's just cosine^
square + sin^ square= 1. Cosine^ square
+ sin^ square= 1. So, they're normalized
both of them. Sin^ 2 + cosine^ 2 is
equal to 1. Again, no complex numbers in
these vectors here. So, we don't have to
worry about complex
conjugation. Next, are they orthogonal?
Let's check that. Cossine theta * - sin
theta plus sin theta * cosine theta.
Obviously, they are orthogonal. Cosine *
minus s plus sin * cosine adds up to
zero. So, yes, they also happen to be
orthogonal to each other.
beta bet theta + / 2 = z. And we've
got yet another basis. We've got yet
another basis of vectors
[Music]
uh for our space of states.
It represents a physically different
kind of experiment. Diff a similar kind
of experiment but different in that the
direction of the polarizers are now uh
uh in an arbitrary direction
theta. Okay. Now we can ask a question.
Supposing we construct one of these
theta photons, a photon polarized along
the theta axis. What's the probability
that if we send it through an X
polarizer that it will pass
through? So let's do that
experiment. I mean this is exactly the
kind of question that quantum mechanics
is set up to
answer. We have our theta polarizer over
here.
We send our photon. I'm going to make a
red photon this time. We send our photon
through. Of course, the photon may not
go through. The photon may have been
polarized in some wrong direction, but
if it gets through, it is then a theta
polarized photon. It's now a theta
polarized photon. And we now send it
through a second polarizer, which I'm
going to take to be an X polarizer.
What's the probability that it goes
through? Does it or doesn't it? And if
it does or doesn't, what's the
probability? This is the kind of
question now that classical mechanics,
it would make no sense in classical
mechanics. And classical mechanics is
deterministic. It either goes through or
it doesn't go through. Okay. So, let's
uh figure it out. All we have to do is
take the inner product between theta
that's our starting vector here in the
middle and
x. The square of this is the
probability. Okay. So what is this? This
is we can we can work it out using the
um the column vectors and row vectors.
The x is the row vector 0 1 0 excuse me
and theta is the column vector cossine
theta sin
theta and that inner product is just
cosine theta 1 * cosine theta plus 0 *
sin theta that inner product is just
cosine of theta. Incidentally notice
that it doesn't
matter whether you take uh whe whether
you take
Either way, x theta or theta x. The
reason is that although in general these
objects are complex and different than
each other, they're complex conjugates
of each other. When you square them or
when multiply by their complex
conjugate, it doesn't matter which order
you put them in. Okay? But in this case,
especially where everything's real, it
certainly doesn't matter. And then the
probability the probability over here
the the question the probability
question this is not the observable this
is the probability this is the
probability that if the photon was
polarized in the theta direction that it
passes through the x
polarizer okay that probability is the
square of this inner product in other
words it's cosine^ 2 theta
Notice it's cosine^ squar theta not not
cosine of
theta. What's the probability that it
passes through the y polarizer? Let's
send it through the y
polarizer. Through the y
[Music]
polarizer. That's going to be very
similar except we're going to put y
here.
And that's
01. This gives us sin
theta. That's going to give us sin^
square theta.
What's the total
probability that it will either pass
through the well the total probability
if we add up the probabilities that it's
x polarized or y polarized it's either x
polarized or y polarized here's the
probability that it's I'm sorry
squared
squared it's either x polarized or y
polarized with probability cosine^ 2
theta and sin^ square theta the total
probability adds up to
Okay, so here's another here's a
slightly more
intricate example of a quantum
mechanical problem where we send
something through at an arbitrary angle
and then measure its polarization along
the vertical or horizontal direction. We
can go further. We could send
it through a
polarizer
in the 45 degree angle. Here we have
enough information to figure out the
probabilities that it'll go through 40
45 pi over two, the pi over two
[Music]
polarizer. But why work that out? Let's
just send it through an arbitrary angle,
the first one, and a second arbitrary
angle, the second one. I'm going to call
those angles, I hate using primes, so
I'm going to call them alpha and
beta. Alpha and beta are also good Greek
letters. When it passes through the
first polarizer, it comes out alpha
polarized. And then we want to know
what's the probability it will pass
through the beta polarizer.
Let's check that and see if we can get a
general
formula which will serve for all
possible
polarizers. What's the answer going to
depend
on? Is it going to depend on alpha times
beta alpha plus
beta? alpha minus beta the relative the
the the angular distance between them
that it better otherwise we're doing
something wrong right okay so let's
check it out all right here here's where
I um either shine
[Music]
or or don't shine okay so let's take the
alpha uh let's take the alpha let's take
the inner product of the alpha vector
with the beta vector the alpha vector
there. Oh, you know, before we do so,
let me do a bit of review of
trigonometry. A review of some
trigonometric formulas that we'll
use. Uh, keep in mind what problem we
want to solve.
Two polarizers at arbitrary angles, but
we need a bit of trigonometry. So, let
me just write down the trigonometric
formulas that we need.
cosine alpha plus
beta equals. Anybody
know cossine alpha cosine
beta
minus sin alpha sin
beta. Now let's while we're at it, let
we're going to wind up also wanting
cosine of alpha minus beta.
And to get the cosine of alpha minus
beta, we just change the sign of beta in
this formula. Changing the sign of beta
does nothing to cosine beta. But it
changes the sign of changes the sign of
sign. It changes the sign of
sign. It changes the sign with a g of
sign without a g. Got it? Okay. So that
gives us cossine alpha cosine beta plus
sin alpha sin beta. Notice we don't
change sin alpha. We haven't done
anything to alpha. We've only done
something to beta.
We will also
need
uh sine of alpha plus
beta and that is equal
[Music]
to sin alpha cossine
beta plus sin
beta cossine
alpha. And while we're at it, let's also
do sine of alpha minus beta.
Again, all I've done is change
beta. It doesn't change the cosine of
beta, but it does change the sign of
beta. So, this becomes sin alpha cosine
beta minus sin beta cosine
alpha. The nice check we can do. What if
alpha equals beta? If alpha equals beta,
we have cosine of 0. Cosine of 0 is
what?
one. All right. On the right hand side,
we would have cosine of alpha squared.
Alpha is equal to beta. Cosine of alpha
squar plus s of alpha squared. That's 1.
Cosine^ square + sin^ squ. So that
works. How about sine of alpha minus
beta? What should that
be? If sorry, if alpha equals beta that
should be zero. So if alpha equals beta,
these two will cancel each
other. Okay. Okay, one more. Cosine of 2
alpha. That's easy. We just read it off
from here. That's cossine^ squar
alpha minus sin^ 2
alpha and sine of 2
alpha. We read from here. That's just uh
twice sin cosine.
All right, here's our trigonometric
table of
formulas and
uh we'll use
them. Okay, so we pass through the per
first polarizer. It's the alpha
polarizer and what comes out is the
alpha k
alpha which is equal to cossine
alpha let's just write it this way
cosine alpha sin
alpha just using this formula replacing
theta by alpha.
So we passed through the alpha polarizer
but now we're testing for beta
polarization. The
beta k is of course cosine beta sin
beta or I really want the uh I really
want the bra vector. So the bra vector
is
beta is equal to the row row of cosine
beta sin beta. We just turn it and make
a row vector out of it. Now what's the
inner product? The inner product of
alpha and
beta beta
alpha is cosine alpha* cosine beta plus
sin alpha * sin
beta and lo and
behold I
hope that's the top formula which is no
it's a second one which is cosine of
alpha minus
beta. Now that's of course not the
probability that's the thing that we
square to get the probability. So the
probability is just cosine squared of
alpha minus
beta. How could you be absolutely sure
that this wasn't the probability even if
you didn't know any quantum mechanics?
Yeah, because it can be negative, right?
All right, here's our formula. Indeed,
it only depends on the difference
between the angles. But let's look at a
little more carefully. First of all,
what happens if beta is very very close
to alpha? In fact, what happens if beta
is equal to alpha? If beta is equal to
alpha, we get cosine^ squar of 0, which
is one. So that simply says that if we
polarize along the alpha direction and
then we send it through a polarizer very
very close to the alpha direction it has
a very high probability of getting
through almost equal to
one cosine alpha minus beta is almost
equal to one if alpha is uh close to
beta and as beta is rotated away from
alpha this gets
smaller when they're 90° apart from each
other, then the cosine uh the cosine of
90° is zero and there's no probability
to go through. So the formula makes some
sense. Formula looks
good. But keep in mind, we're doing
something interesting and unusual. There
are only two possible outcomes to the
beta experiment over here.
There are only two possible things that
can come out of the alpha polarizer over
here. And yet we're
finding answers, but answers which are
probabilistic. Answers which are
probabilistic and equal to the square of
quantum mechanical amplitudes. These
inner products are called amplitudes.
Their squares are
probabilities. All right. Uh let's see.
Should we take a uh let's take a few
minutes
break. And what we haven't done yet is
found the observable for a general
polarization. The observable for general
polarization we'll do
next. All right. So two people asked me
an interesting question.
uh and uh it sort of does point out one
of
the somewhat mildly I don't know it
depends on who I've known it for so long
that to me it's mildly freaky but uh
here here's the issue supposing you send
a photon through a polarizer which is
polarized let's say in the theta
direction not horizontally definitely
not horizontally but in some arbitrary
direction and then you're going to send
it through a second polarizer or third
I'm going to call this the third
polarizer up here far away and it's
polarized in the orthogonal direction
theta plus pi /
2 of course the first
photon may or may not get through but
let's suppose it gets
through it's polarized in the theta
direction and it will not make it
through the theta plus p /2
polarizer but supposing we put in
between a polarizer let's say in the
vertical direction or let's make it the
horizontal direction for no good reason
other than
uh then does it get through or doesn't
it get through? The answer is it gets
through with a
probability. The probability we can
calculate. Let's calculate the
probability. Um
well let's let's work it out. I don't
know. I haven't worked it out first. The
first question is what's the probability
that it gets through the horizontal
polarizer? All right, I think we have a
formula for the horizontal polarizer
that corresponds to beta equals 0. And
the answer was just cosine^ 2
theta. There's a probability cosine^ 2
theta that the photon makes it through
the first polarizer here. cosine^ 2
theta. But now when it makes it through
the first polarizer, it is now polarized
in the horizontal direction. It is no
longer polarized in the theta direction.
If it makes it through, it's polarized
in the horizontal direction. So what's
the probability that it goes through the
third polarizer? It is cosine^
[Music]
squar of now we have to take the angle
over here minus the angle over here
that's 0
- + theta / 2 cossine of uh so it's
cosine of theta + p / 2 which is
what sin^ 2
theta I think I Did that
right? Not a not added but multiplied.
The probability that it goes through the
first one is cosine^ 2 theta. And then
if it does it's horizontally polarized.
If it's horizontally polarized then the
probability that it goes through the
second polarizer is sin^ square
theta which is the same as cosine^ 2 of
theta + p / 2.
What's that?
Well,
[Music]
say it again.
This is this is less than one. Right.
There is less than one. So it comes so
it passes through this polarizer with a
probability less than one. Each time you
cut down the probability. So the
probability if you do a lot of
polarizers like this of course will go
down uh with the number of
polarizers but by putting this one in
you take a photon which was polarized in
the theta direction and could not go
through the second one and now allow it.
So this is one of the uh whether you
find this anti-intuitive or not uh is uh
He gets it gets an assist
for if you actually do that um you'll
get based on the angle in between you
actually get a different color if you
start off with it may be but I don't
know why
it's so maybe so I don't I I don't know
why it's true though Uh seems like well
polariz
yeah well um yeah but do keep in mind
that polarizers have different
efficiencies for different colors so it
might I would have to think about it but
it's also used as stress test for yeah I
yeah I that that's true I've seen them
do things like that um so I I don't know
offhand I would have to think about why
that's true but it probably has to do
with the fact that the efficiency for
polarizations is is frequency.
Yeah, I think the high frequency goes
through because the slits are too wide
perhaps. Let me think about it. I I I
it's completely something I didn't even
know. So, uh so I need to I need to
dwell on it a little bit. Okay, good.
interesting fact if it's true. But this
is kind of an interesting quantum
mechanical fact that
um it's an interference effect. It's a
funny kind of interference effect that
something you would have thought that by
that whatever the probability to go
through the second polarizer was. You
would have diminished it by putting
something in the way. Huh? By putting
something else in the way which cuts
down the probability. You would have
thought that you diminish the
probability. Well, as you can see, it's
not always true. So, this is one of
these interference
phenomena. Okay, let's see if we can
find the
um the observable. Now, we're not
learning very much by figuring out the
observables in these cases. I just want
to show you that they exist. They make
sense. Their igen values and igen
vectors are correct
uh are are correct.
There are lots of other cases where we
know much more about the observables
than we do about anything else and then
we work in the opposite direction. But
okay, we're interested now in the
observable
representing polarization in the theta
direction. In other words, by
definition, this one's a little bit
thicker. By
definition, P theta acting on
theta gives us plus
theta and P
theta acting on theta + p /
2 gives us
minus theta + p / 2.
In other words, both of these
vectors, both of these polarization
states, theta theta + pi / 2, they're
both igen vectors of the observable
polarization, but igen vectors with
opposite value. Let's see if we can I'm
not going to I'm not going to see if we
can find it. I'm going to write down the
answer and then show you that it works.
Uh, it took me about 15, well less than
15 minutes, 10 minutes to work it
out. And all I did was solve. I simply
wrote these as algebraic equations and
solve the algebraic equations
component-wise. Uh, it was not very
illuminating, but it's mildly
illuminating to see the answer. and then
check it. So the answer
is where is the answer? Here it
[Applause]
is P
theta is equal to
cosine minus
cosine
sine s. But cosine and s of what?
Anybody want to guess?
theta. Let's check that when this object
acts on theta, it gives back theta. So,
let me erase the left side of the
equation here because it's not going to
be an equation anymore. Let's multiply
it by theta. Now uh let me first rewrite
this cosine of 2 theta cosine of 2 theta
is cossine^ 2 theta minus sin^ 2 theta
that's in the upper left here we have
twice cossine theta sin theta do anybody
mind if instead of writing cosine theta
and sin theta I'm just going to write c
and
s c and s for cosine and sin theta there
will be no confusion since there's only
one angle here. So this is C ^2 minus
S^2. This is TW S c. This is
twice S C and this is S^2 minus C ^
2. And we want to apply this now to
theta. What is theta? Theta
is
CS. Look up on the upper right
corner.
CS. Okay, let's just work it
out. Okay, so we have to multiply C ^2
minus S^2 by C.
So in the upper place we have c^
2 c^ 2 c minus s^ 2
c that's this times this plus s c *
s plus twice s c *
s. What about in the bottom? In the
bottom we have twice sc
*
c twice s I leave it that way s c * c
plus s^2 s - c^2 s
Okay, don't ask me why I wrote it in
this clumsy way. I don't know why. We
have twice s 2 c over here. This is
twice s 2 c over
here. But we have minus s^2 c over here.
So the +2 and the minus1 conspire to
change this to a plus sign and we get
rid of
this. Now we have c ^ 2 + s 2 * c. c is
a common factor in both of them. So
let's take c
outside. And now what is c ^2 + s squ?
1. So this is just
C. That's good because we want to get
remember what we're trying to get that P
theta on theta just gives us back
theta. Okay. Now let's look at the lower
piece here. Twice S
c here's minus
cs. So the two again conspires with a
minus sign turns it into a plus
sign and now we
have s 2 s + c ^2 s and that's just
s. So we check explicitly that p theta
on theta gives us back theta. And I'll
leave it to you to check that P theta on
uh on
on this guy here gives
minus itself back again. So these two
vectors where are they? CS and minus S C
are the igen vectors of the
[Music]
observable. The observable is
hermission. How do you tell that it's
hermission? Remember what hermission
means? Hermission means that if you
reflect about the diagonal and complex
conjugate, you get back to the same
thing. For real matrices, we're going to
talk more about hermission, but for real
matrices, hermission just means
symmetric. This is a hermission matrix.
It's igen vectors and igen values
satisfy certain requirements. The igen
vectors are orthogonal. The igen values
are real. This is the observable that
goes with the polarization along the
angle
theta. What happens
incidentally? Interesting question.
Supposing I took
this here's the observable for angle
[Music]
theta. What is the
observable for minus theta?
What happens to minus theta to the
observable minus
theta? That's not really what I want to
do, is it? I don't think that's what I
actually want to do.
Um, no, that's not what I wanted to do.
Sorry, that's
uh what I wanted to do was to look at
the observable for theta plus pi / 2.
for theta + pi / 2. What happens to
observable for theta + pi / 2?
Uh what should happen to
it? This is theta. What's the cosine
of theta of twice
theta?
Okay, here's
theta. Here's theta + pi /
2. And where is twice that angle?
Minus cosine 2 theta. Right. So if we do
that transformation, if we rotate by
90°, this becomes minus cossine 2 theta.
This one will become plus cossine 2
theta. And what about s of theta +
p / 2 also just changes sign,
right? So this becomes minus.
In other words, what's happened by
focusing on the um observable rotated by
90 degrees, it's just changed sign.
Well, that makes a lot of sense because
all it's done is interchange the
positive igen value with a negative igen
value. It's just interchange the
value. The observable for theta has igen
values plus one and minus one for the
two states. the observable for the
rotated 90° just interchanges the plus
sign and the minus sign. That's all I
wanted to say that uh that it
interchanges the plus sign and the minus
sign. Okay, so that also makes
sense. Okay, we've left out of the story
an important ingredient another kind of
polarization that there is another kind
of polarization
must be so because we haven't introduced
any imaginary numbers
yet. Remember quantum mechanics is all
about complex
numbers and there's nothing to pre
prevent us from introducing state
vectors with complex numbers in them.
For example, here's a state vector with
a complex number in it. 1
I. Is that normalized? No, it's not
normalized. Uh remember what we have to
do. We have to multiply each one by its
complex conjugate and add them to find
the normalization. 1^2 is 1. I 2 I *
minus I is also 1. We need a 1 over
two here.
This is a perfectly good normalized
state vector in quantum
mechanics. We may not know what it is
yet. And in fact, I'm I'm eventually
going to tell you what it
is, but it has to be there. It has to be
some kind of uh new state vector. It can
also be written as 1 over 2 x + i
over 2
Why? It's something that doesn't have an
obvious interpretation in terms of uh
these
angles. Is there a vector which is
orthogonal to it? Of course, there must
be another vector which is orthogonal to
it. The orthogonal one is 1 / 2 * 1
-
i. Let's check that these two are
orthogonal to each other. Well, 1 * 1 is
1. I * - i is 1. If I add them up, I get
two. That's no good. No, but something's
wrong with that. I forgot the complex
conjugate. I forgot the complex
conjugate. If I want to see whether
these two are orthogonal, one of them
has to be a bra vector. Let's take this
one to be a bra vector. So that means it
corresponds to the um uh to the row
vector 1 over
two 1 +
i. Not 1 plus i but one and i.
not minus I but I and that's because we
have to complex conjugate in the bra
vectors. All right, let's take the inner
product of this
with one I with another square root of
two. That'll just get rid of the square
root of two here and put a 1/2
there. But now we can see this is 1 * 1
+ i * i and that's zero.
Okay, so these two vectors are indeed
orthogonal. There must be
some observable which distinguishes
them. I'm going to leave it to you as a
homework problem to find the
observable with the following property.
I I'll give it to you next time, but I'm
going to leave it assign it as a
homework problem uh for fun. I'm not
going to collect it. So, but
and try out your
uh this one I will
call
that. This one I will call that. And
guess what they are? They are circular
polarization. Light can also be
circularly polarized. Let me tell you
what circularly polarized light means
from the wave point of view. From the
wave point of
view, it clearly means that there is
both X and Y polarization mixed
in. X and Y polarization are both mixed
in here. Uh, in fact, if I were to
calculate, and I will in a moment, if I
were to calculate the probability that
it passes through an X polarizer, it'll
be 1/2. A Y polarizer, it'll also be
1/2. In fact, we'll see that it passes
through probability 1/2 through any one
of the theta polarizers, right? But uh
so
it's got both x and y mixed into
it as we can see. Um what was I going to
say about it? Yeah. So from the point of
view of wave theory, it must have the
electric field is both in the x and y
direction. In fact, it has more or less
it has equal probability for being in
the x and y direction. The magnitude of
one and the magnitude of i is the same.
So it looks like somehow it's a state
with let's think about now the electric
field electric field going into the
blackboard. It looks like it has an
electric field in the x direction and an
electric field in the y direction. You
would think that adds up to an electric
field like that and that it ought to
just be a polarization in the 45 degree
direction. But that's not right. That's
not what a circularly polarized light
ray is. What a circularly polarized
light ray. Let's think about a
vertically polarized lightweight light
wave that has an electric
field which is something like for
example cosine of Z. It's moving down
the
Z-axis minus CT. This is a way of moving
C is the speed of light. This is a wave
of moving down the Z-axis with the speed
of light.
And this could be the y polarization or
this could be the y
component of an electromagnetic wave
moving down the
z-axis. The x
component, if I wrote that that was also
equal to cosine of z minus
ct, that would correspond to a plain
polarized light ray at 45°.
In other words, it would just say that
the component of the electric field in
the 45 degree axis was was uh was uh
cosine or square of 2 * cosine of z
+ ct minus
ct.
But we put them out of
phase. We put them out of phase. What
that
means now these are the electric fields.
No magnetic field. I have not mixed in
the magnetic field at all. What this
says is if we look here's the z-axis
down
here here's x the electric field might
be a cosine and look like
this whereas the s whereas the other
component of the electric field the y
component is a sign.
So where the x component is maximum the
y component is zero and so on. I don't
know if I can draw this.
I can never do this. I can never get
them out. The thing to do is to draw
them in phase and then shift
them. Now take the red one and shift it
by 90 degrees. I can never do that. 90
degrees is uh halfway and I'm not good
at halfway things. Just take the red one
and shift it by 90 degrees so that where
the y component of the electric field is
maximum the x component is minimum. If
you stand at a point, let's say the
point Z equals
Z. Stand at the point Z equals
Z and look at the X and Y
component of the electric field. What
does it
do? It rotates around in a circle.
These are the equations for
a for an electric field. Here's the
electric field. It has an x component
that has a y
component. When the x component is
maximum, the y component is minimum and
vice versa. This is an electric field
which is just rotating
around with a uniform angular
motion. That's called a circularly
polarized wave. It's a perfectly good
wave. It's just a wave whose x and y
component are out of phase with respect
to each other. It's another another
solution of Maxwell's equations.
Incidentally, the magnetic fields are
the same as the electric fields except
rotated by 90 degrees. So uh you could
write something similar for the magnetic
fields. There are two possibilities ey=
cosine ex= s and ey= cosine ex= minus
sign. One of them rotates around in one
direction. The other one rotates around
in the other direction. Those are pl
those are circularly polarized light
waves. And the individual photons of a
circularly polarized light wave are
called circularly polarized
photons. I've labeled them this way. And
this is the state vectors that describe
them. Left polarization and right
polarization. I might have left and
right mixed up. Uh it's not very
important for us right now.
What kind of device was that? A circular
polarizer.
How do you make a circular polarizer?
Anybody know?
Uh next time I'll describe how you make
a circular polarizer. A quarter wave
plate is the right answer. But
uh
um it is what gets the x and y
components out of phase. But there are
two new kinds of photons. Of course,
they're not really independent kinds of
photons. They are new circularly
polarized photons. But what happens if I
send a cir? Let's ask the following
question. What happens if I send a
circularly polarized photon
through a theta
polarizer? Okay. What happens if I send
a circularly polarized photon through a
theta polarizer? Well, to answer that,
in other words, what's the probability
that it goes through? Again, we take the
inner product of the circular polarized
photon. Here it is with the theta
polarized photon and we square it. I
won't square it yet. I'll square it
after we calculate it. So, let's see.
The circularly polarized photon has 1
over
two and I over
two for its K vector. And the theta
polarized one has what is it? Cosine
theta sin
theta. Did I get that
right?
Good. Okay. So what's the answer? Let's
see. We get 1 over 2. The inner
product then is 1 / 2 cossine
theta
plus i over square of 2 sin
theta. That's the inner product or
that's the amplitude the quantum
mechanical amplitude. Now we want to
calculate the probability. To calculate
the probability we have to multiply this
by its complex conjugate. So let's do
that up here. This times its complex
conjugate is cosine. Let's just write
let's just call it
C over two. Well, 1 over
times C + I
S and then another one over square
of two for uh
we're going to yeah we're square
multiplying this by its complex
conjugate. So another 1 over two *
c - i
s gives us
12 c^ 2 + s^
2 i * - i is plus so it's c ^ 2 + s^ 2
which is just 12.
In other words, as you might have
expected, for a circularly polarized
photon, there's probability 1/2 that it
will go through any linearly polarized
uh you cannot tell what direction your
polarizer is polarized in by the fact
that the circular polarization goes
through with a probability of half.
Whatever the whatever the direction of
the linear polarized polarizer is, the
circular polarized photon will go
through with probability
1/2. You can also say the opposite is
also true. A linearly polarized photon
has a probability 1/2 to go through the
circular go through the quarter wave
plate which makes
um uh which makes circular polarization.
But we'll come to that next time. Okay.
So this is the basic um setup of
circular polarization. Of course once
you realize that complex numbers are
allowed then you can put in any complex
numbers here any pair of complex
numbers. This will be an allow any pair
such that the sums of the squares come
come out to be one. And those define a
wider class of polarizations which are
elliptically polarized photons.
Elliptically polarized photons are
circularly polarized
when one of these is real and one of
them is
imaginary. If both of them are almost
real, one of them is real and one of
them is close to being real, then it's
an elliptical polarization, which is
almost a plain polarized photon. Well, I
think we'll do a little more with
elliptical polarized photons uh next
time if I get a
chance. But
uh
the and don't ask me how you make a
polarizer that polarizes elliptical
photons that uh well actually you can
ask me next time. I will have an answer
for you. I just realized I know how to
do it. Um
good. All right. But we're essentially
finished with the idea of polarization
uh photon polarization for the time
being. We may come back to it as a as an
example. But uh first of all, one thing
which is
obvious bunch Oh, I have not defined for
you. I'll do it next time. The
observable that goes with circular
polarization. It's got some imaginary
numbers in it. Well, I'll know that by
then. You should know that. Yeah. Oh,
that's right. I did I was that the
homework? That's the homework. Yeah.
Good. All right. So, that's the
homework. Find the observable that goes
with the circular polar
polarization. But you're going to find
if you find them all that for any two
different polarizations, circular,
linear, or anything else, the
polarization observables don't commute
with each other. That's more or less
obvious because they certainly don't
ever have common igen vectors. The igen
vectors of the this polarization are one
zero. The igen vectors of this
polarization are equal mixtures of one
of the x and y. And the circular
polarizations have i's in them. They
have no common igen vectors for
different polarizations. The implication
of that is that the polarization
observables do not commute for different
uh for different directions or type of
polarization. The implication of that is
for example that you cannot measure
simultaneously
the x
polarization. Can you measure
simultaneously the x polarization and
the y
polarization? Yes. X and Y. Yes. If the
x polarization is plus, then the y
polarization is certainly minus. They're
trivial. They're they're they're simply
related to each other in such a simple
way. And in fact, the x the x
polarization and the y polarization are
just negatives of each other. But how
about the xolarization and the 45
polarization? No, those you cannot
measure simultaneously. the x
polarization and the 45 polar and the
slash polarization. You cannot
simultaneously measure the x
polarization and the circular
polarization
uh because the observables don't
commute and the observables for a
theta and for theta plus pi / 2 do
commute. They're just the negatives of
each other. That's what I showed you a
few minutes ago that that P
theta is just equal to
minus P theta + pi /
2. That's just interchanging the
positive and negative values. A thing
certainly commutes with its negative. So
the
polarization for theta and for theta
plus pi / 2 can be simultaneously
measured. In fact, when you measure one,
you automatically know the other. It's
just a negative of it. But none of these
commute if the angles are genuinely
different. So those are examples of
incompatible
variables. And it just says that you
can't have a polarizer which polarizes
both in the x direction and the theta
direction.
Uh it's something more or less obvious.
Okay, I want to come to a one thing that
we have not discussed the idea of
expectation value which really should
just be called average
value. Expectation value is a poor
choice of terminology. Let me explain
why right now. Supposing I have a wave
function for a particle that looks like
this. That's what you want if you're an
animal. Well, I don't know. Not in this
case, I don't
think. All right. There's a wave
function which is nice and symmetric. It
has a lump over here and a lump over
here. Uh this could be x x0 over here.
What's the average value of x? It looks
good. Zero. What's the what uh and and
let's suppose this have a tails over
here, tails over here, and actually goes
right to zero here. What's the least
likely uh answer that you could get?
You'll never get the average. You'll
never get the average. So the le the
last thing you expect is the expectation
value.
It should not be called the expectation
value. Even worse, Murray Galman insists
on calling it the expected value. It
is it is not the expected value. It's
the average value that we're defining
that I'm going to define now. So let's
uh let me define for you
the average value by first writing down
a mathematical expression for it and
then showing you that it really is the
average value. Suppose you have some
observable K any observable whatever
hermission operator
K and I have some state it could be the
position operator it could be the
momentum operator it could be one of our
polarization operators the only thing
about it is that it's hermission and it
corresponds to some observable it has a
collection of igen vectors and IGEN
values lambda n and
n these this is the observable here are
its igen values here are its igen
vectors. K acting on the igen vector n
gives lambda n * n. All right, that's
the definition. Now take any state
whatever I'll call it
s operate with
k. K is an operator. It hits any vector
and creates a new vector and then take
its inner product with sigh itself
again. In other words, it's a sandwich
where the bread is the bra vector and
Kve vector sigh and the baloney in the
middle is uh is the observable K.
H no star star.
No no star. No K is a hermission thing.
Oh yeah, the bra means that it's complex
conjugated. It effectively means it's
complex conjugated. Whenever you see a
bra, it always implies complex
conjugation. Just another symbol for
complex
conjugation. All right, let's calculate
this. Let's calculate it by
inserting complete sets of states.
Remember that these n vectors here are a
complete orthonormal family, a basis of
vectors. And let me just remind you of
the basic rule that if I make the diad n
and sum over
n, that's just equal to the identity
operator and can be stuck into any
expression for free without changing
it. Since n is a summation index, I
could also call it
m. It would still be the identity
operator. It doesn't matter what I call
this. It's a summation index.
Okay, let's put such a basis of vectors
in
here.
Si k hat. And now right over here
n
summed over
n. I have not changed it. This is equal.
This is equal to this. But now what does
K do when it hits N?
K on N equals lambda N on
N. So we can rewrite this as sum on
n
[Music]
s
n
si lambda n. What I've done is I've said
that k when it hits n just multiplies it
by the number lambda n. Now n is still
inside the sum.
Okay, let's erase
this. Everybody see what I did? I stuck
the complete basis N between K and S.
Then I said that K when it hits N just
multiplies by lambda
N. Now what is this? S in a product with
N times N inner product with S.
This
is s
n times its complex
conjugate time lambda n. And what is s n
times its complex
conjugate? It's a probability.
The inner product of a state vector with
a basis vector representing an
observable K is the
probability that the system has igen
value lambda N. So what this
is is it's the
sum on n of the probability that if you
were to measure K, you would get the nth
value times the nth
value. For
example, if I plot lambda n this way,
these are the these are the
lambdas. Here's lambda 1, lambda 2,
lambda 3, lambda 4, lambda
5, and each one has a probability.
Here's the
probabilities.
Just what do you get? If you add up all
the probabilities times the igen value,
you get the
average the
average of lambda.
In other words, it's the probability
times the thing which you're measuring
summed over all the do is this obvious
to
everybody that um that if you sum over
all the possible values that you can get
for a
measurement, you sum over all the
possible values you get for the
measurement with the value for the
measurement that you get times the
probability that you get that value.
That is called the average. The average
of lambda or you could say that it's the
average of K of the observable
K. Better
yet, the quantum mechanical
notation is
just K representing this thing over
here. This is the symbol that's often
used for the average of a quantity just
bracket in between uh without being
without particularly writing down the
vector here. It's just a notation
represents the average and you can see
that what it is is just a sandwich of
the observable evaluated
between the same between the bra vector
and the k vector representing the state
of the system. This is why it's often
useful to actually have these
observables if you're interested in
calculating the average value of a
measurement. Then if you have if you
know the vector that you've prepared, in
other words, if you know what you've
prepared, sigh, and you know the
observable, you just sandwich it in this
way. Okay. Uh let's do an
example. I'm tired, so I'm going to do
the very simplest example.
My observable is just going to be 1
minus one 0 0. This is the observable
polarization in the xy plane. And now
let's take uh something um uh the
vector
theta. In other words, a linear
polarization polarized in the theta
direction. Okay. What is the average
value of this observable? Well, we take
theta, we put
P and we take theta again. We make a
sandwich.
Okay. In terms of matrices, that's 1 0 0
1. The K vector over here is cossine
theta sin theta.
And the bra vector is just the row
vector also cossine theta sin
theta. What do I get when I this is
minus one excuse
me? Okay just take two minutes to work
it out. Multiplying the matrix by the
vector what does that do? It just
changes the sign of the bottom entry. So
it just gives you cossine
theta sin
theta time cossine theta minus sin
theta. That inner product is cossine^ 2
theta - sin^ 2
theta which is also something else.
cosine 2 cosine 2
theta. All right. So we found out what
the
average of this observable is. It
clearly lies between one and minus one.
It could hardly be bigger than one or
smaller than minus one.
And depending on the direction of
polarization, the average will just be
cosine of twice the
angle. Uh you can check that out and see
if it makes any sense to you by trying
it out for some angles and seeing if it
makes sense. But we could do the same
thing with any observable.
We could c and any observable and any
vector we could calculate the pro the uh
not the probability but the average of
the uh of the observable. I will use the
standard terminology and call it the
expectation value but keep in mind that
that really is a misnomer. It should be
just the average
value. Good. I think we're finished for
tonight.
The preceding program was brought to you
by Stanford on iTunes U and is
copyrighted by the board of trustees of
the Leland Stanford Jr. University.
Please visit us at iTunes.stanford.edu.
edu.